I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we have the second
in a two part series
where I offer some highlights from
my latest book, How Not to Age,
taped in front of
a live audience.
We pick up our
story with tips
on how to keep our vital organs
in good working order.
What can we do to protect our
bones, bowels, bladder, and circulation?
Our hair, hearing,
and hormone balance?
Immune function,
joint health?
Our minds and our muscles?
Sex life and skin?
Our teeth, vision, and finally,
our dignity in death.
Let me just share
a few quick pearls.
For example,
did you know that 85 percent
of bone-related fracture risk
has nothing to do with
your bone mineral density?
That’s just been drilled
into our heads by big pharma
and a billion-dollar bone
density screening industry.
Fractures are primarily due
to falling, not osteoporosis.
So, it’s the age-related muscle
loss and impaired balance
that may be breaking
most of our bones—
which is good news,
because there’s something
we can do something about it.
Seven randomized
controlled trials
found that strength
and balance training
can cut fracture
rates nearly in half—
and that’s just
during the trial.
In the five years after this
one-year study ended,
those who had previously
been randomized
to the combined strength
and balance group,
suffered 74 percent
fewer fractures.
That’s far more effective than
osteoporosis drugs like Fosamax
that can cause fractures—
atypical femoral fractures,
in as many as
1 in 300 users.
They are called “atypical,”
because they occur
not after a fall or trauma
but just during routine
activities, like walking,
twisting at the hip,
or even just standing still.
Thanks to the drug,
your femur, your thigh bone,
the biggest bone in your body—
just cracks in half.
Too cruel an irony from a drug
that’s supposed to protect your bones.
After bones,
I talk about preserving
your bowel function
in chapter number two.
Randomize constipated
diabetics
to either cookies containing
a tablespoon (20 g) a day
of ground flaxseeds
or flax-free placebo
cookies for 12 weeks
and not only does the flax
improve constipation symptoms
but resulted in an eight-pound
weight loss over placebo,
25-point lower
blood sugars,
an astounding drop in hemoglobin A1c,
and 17-point lower LDL cholesterol.
All for about 10 cents a day
of ground flaxseeds.
For a head-to-head test
between flaxseeds and psyllium,
sold as Metamucil,
a third cookie group was added
with 10 grams of psyllium,
and the flaxseed beat out the
psyllium for constipation relief,
weight, blood sugars,
and cholesterol—
and, is about four
times cheaper.
Flaxseeds were also directly compared
to the prescription laxative lactulose
and worked better as well.
Bladder function!
The prevalence of overactive
bladder syndrome increases with age,
reaching about
one in three.
No wonder bladder-relaxing drugs
are a multibillion-dollar industry,
yet may only reduce
bathroom breaks
by a half a pee a day
compared to placebo.
But a quarter teaspoon (500 mg) a day
of dried cranberry powder
worked nearly
four times better,
about two fewer daily trips
to the bathroom over placebo,
and that’s without any of
the drug’s side effects:
dry mouth, constipation,
sedation, impaired cognition,
rapid heartbeat,
urinary retention,
and the visual disturbances
that lead almost two-thirds
to stop taking the drugs,
whereas cranberries
are just tangy.
Urinary incontinence is a common
problem among older adults,
particularly women,
thanks to childbirth.
Systemic menopausal hormone therapy
like Premarin actually makes it worse,
but local, vaginal
estrogen may help.
What works five times better
than estrogen cream though?
Kegel exercises,
pelvic floor exercises,
as I detail in the section
“Jacked in the Box.”
For men, urinary issues are more
an enlarged prostate problem,
having to get up
multiple times at night,
wee hours of the night.
Cranberries to the
rescue there again.
Even just an eighth of a teaspoon (250 mg)
a day of powdered cranberries
can significantly improve
prostate symptoms.
You can buy cranberry
powder in bulk
at a cost of less than
a penny per day.
What about
saw palmetto,
the most common herbal supplement
used for prostate symptoms?
Based on dozens of randomized,
controlled trials
involving nearly 5,000 men:
no clinical benefits.
But pumpkin seeds work.
More than a thousand men with
prostate symptoms were randomized
to either about a tablespoon (15 g) a day
of plain pumpkin seed kernels,
a proprietary pumpkin seed
extract, or a placebo.
The study was funded by the drug
company that made the supplement,
but the supplement
totally flopped,
while the pumpkin seeds
themselves worked.
Pumpkin seed oil was pitted against
the leading drug for hair loss in women.
A little less than a quarter teaspoon (1 ml)
applied to the scalp once a day
versus a dose of the drug,
and they both worked,
but the drug worked better.
Rosemary oil, however,
may be more closely matched.
A hundred balding men were randomized
to twice a day minoxidil like Rogaine
versus a rosemary lotion.
It took six months,
but significant comparable improvement
in hair counts in both groups,
with no significant difference
between the two.
The rosemary lotion appeared
to work as well as the drug.
If you want to
give it a DIY try,
you can premix about 10 drops
of rosemary essential oil
to each fluid ounce (30 ml)
of your favorite lotion
and rub a quarter teaspoon (1.23 ml)
into your scalp twice a day.
Cost-wise,
that much rosemary oil
would come out to be
about a penny per week.
Let’s move on from hair
highlights to hormones.
I touched upon how
menopausal hormone therapy
can increase the risk of urinary
incontinence, but that’s not all.
If a thousand
postmenopausal women
take the standard hormone
regimen for ten years,
you’d not only expect 876
extra cases of urinary incontinence
that they would not
have got otherwise,
but nine more cases of
invasive breast cancer,
eight more cases
of heart disease,
probably 22 more
cases of dementia,
21 more cases of
gallbladder disease,
nine more strokes,
and 21 more blood clots—
though not a single
partridge nor pear tree.
However, hormone
therapy is highly effective
in decreasing
menopausal hot flashes.
Is there any way to keep cool
without the clots and cancer?
In the U.S., menopausal hot
flashes are considered inevitable,
but there isn’t even a word
for hot flash in Japanese.
This may be due to their
greater consumption of soy foods,
but you don’t really know
until you put it to the test.
Harvard’s Center of Excellence
in Women’s Health
funded a randomized,
crossover trial
of a half a cup (118 ml) of
unsalted soy nuts a day
and achieved about a 40 to 45
percent reduction in hot flashes
within two weeks compared
to the control group.
Given that a plant-based
diet may also be effective
for managing
menopausal symptoms,
researchers decided to combine the two:
a plant-based diet plus whole soybeans.
In fact, two randomized controlled trials
found that plant-based nutrition
with a daily half cup (86 g) of
cooked whole soybeans
can reduce the number of serious
hot flashes by 84 to 88 percent
within twelve weeks.
Overall, most randomized to
the plant-based bean group
ended up free of
moderate-to-severe hot flashes
compared to about 95 percent
still suffering in the control group.
Lots of other
things can help.
Whole fennel seeds,
powdered into capsules
to pit them against placebo
in a double-blind trial significantly
improved menopausal symptoms
at a dose of just
a teaspoon (2 g) a day.
Fenugreek may also help at a dose
of one and a half teaspoons (6 g) a day,
though not as much as hormones,
but without the side effects.
Though fenugreek can make your
pee smell like maple syrup,
sounds like a bonus!
The nice thing about
studying spices
is that entire servings
can be stuffed into a pill,
to pit them
against placebo.
A quarter teaspoon (1 g) of
black cumin powder a day
led to significant
improvements in memory
and other tests of cognition within
nine weeks compared to placebo.
Black sesame seeds—
less than a teaspoon (2.52 g) a day
of ground black sesame seeds—
stuffed into capsules
against placebo,
drove down systolic blood pressures
by eight points within a month.
If sustained, that alone could decrease
the risk of stroke by about a quarter.
What else can we powder?
Strawberries!
Osteoarthritis patients
were randomized
to two ounces (50 g) of freeze-
dried strawberry powder
versus a fake, strawberry-flavored
and colored placebo powder,
and, compared to placebo,
the real strawberries signiﬁcantly
decreased constant pain,
intermittent pain,
and total knee pain,
and improved disability
and overall quality of life.
Osteoarthritis is the most frequent cause
of physical disability among older adults,
yet how do we treat it?
Acetaminophen—Tylenol is
considered the first-line pain killer,
but guess what:
it doesn’t work.
I mean—it works,
just not much better
than a sugar pill,
but at least it’s not going
to make matters worse,
like other things we doctors have
cooked up, like steroid injections,
which actively worsen
joint deterioration
and offer no greater
pain relief than placebos.
Or arthroscopic surgery,
which may end up
tripling our risk
of ending up having to get
a total full knee replacement.
I mean so, even if the strawberry
study is some total fluke,
what’s the worst that can
happen, tastier smoothies?
And less than a quarter of a teaspoon
(~1.25 ml) of ground ginger a day
can beat out placebo
for joint pain.
Researchers conclude
ginger, "therefore,
is recommended as a safe
drug for these patients,”
but by “drug” they just mean
a couple pinches of the ground ginger
you can buy
at any store.
There was even a
study on topical ginger—
at least, when applied
to the scrotum.
Paper-thin slices of ginger
applied over the inflamed testicles,
and the researchers
were, on the ball,
healing nearly three times
faster than the control group.
There have been more than a hundred
randomized, controlled trials on ginger,
shown to help with
nausea and vomiting
and everything from
COVID to PMS.
Heavy periods,
painful periods,
migraine headaches,
multiple sclerosis,
and the list goes on.
Bottom line: “Mounting evidence suggests
ginger can promote healthy aging.”
What about garlic?
Clinically proven to protect against
those who vant to suck your blood.
Literally.
A hundred marines were randomized
to a clove a day or placebo,
and those on garlic had
significantly fewer tick bites.
Though sadly, garlic does not appear
to help against other bloodsuckers.
So far, I’ve touched on
preserving your bones, bowels,
bladder, hair,
hormones, and joints,
but preserving your mind is
the largest chapter in the book,
because dementia is one of our
most pressing public health problems
and the most feared
condition of later life.
There’s a common misconception
that we have no control
over whether we
develop dementia,
but the good news is that although
Alzheimer’s may be incurable,
at least it is preventable.
There is an
emerging consensus,
that “what is good for our hearts
is also good for our heads."
Clogged with cholesterol,
closing off our arteries—
clamping down
on blood flow.
What kind of brain arteries
do you want in your head?
Too much cholesterol in our blood is
unanimously recognized to be a risk factor
for the development of
Alzheimer’s disease.
Those with a total
cholesterol of 225 mg/dL or more
may have nearly
25 times the odds
of ending up with amyloid plaques
in their brain 10 to 15 years later.
Cholesterol explains how the Alzheimer's
gene APOE4 ravages the brain.
After all, APOE is the primary
cholesterol carrier in the brain.
LDL cholesterol in those with
bad gene variants of APOE
averages 40 points higher,
but switch people to a
diet lower in animal fat
and that cholesterol difference
can be effectively smoothed out.
So, diet can trump genetics.
This may explain the
so-called Nigerian paradox,
where they have among the
highest rates of the Alzheimer's gene
but some of the lowest rates
of Alzheimer’s disease.
How is that possible?
Genes load the gun,
but lifestyle pulls the trigger.
The paradox may be explained
by their low cholesterol levels,
probably because of their
diets low in animal fat.
Human beings may
have evolved
to maintain an LDL cholesterol
level of around 25 mg/dL,
but the average in the Western
world is approximately 120 mg/dL.
No wonder heart disease is
the leading cause of death
in high income countries,
and dementia is killer #2.
That helps explain why the
so-called Alzheimer’s gene
is the single most important gene
when it comes to longevity, too.
Which is good news,
because even if we’ve been
dealt some bad genetic cards,
we still may be able to
reshuffle the deck with diet.
So, in terms of dietary guidelines
for the prevention of Alzheimer’s,
we should center our diets
around vegetables, legumes,
fruits, and whole grains.
In other words, the dietary
pillar of lifestyle medicine:
whole food,
plant-based, nutrition.
Or even simpler, plants,
plants, and more plants.
Any plants in particular?
Note that the directors of Loma Linda’s
Alzheimer’s Prevention Program
single out berries
and greens.
Eating strawberries
and spinach
can mitigate age-related
cognitive decline in rats,
but what about in people?
When the cognition of hundreds
of twins was followed over a decade,
consuming the berry pigments in less
than a quarter cup (23 g) of blueberries a day
or about a daily
cup (138 g) of strawberries
was associated with slowed
cognitive aging by about four years,
and nearly all of the randomized
controlled trials of blueberries
and cognitive performance found
improvements in at least one brain domain,
perhaps, because blueberry
consumption can improve blood flow
to certain critical
regions of the brain.
Now, the one study that flopped
mixed the berries with milk,
and we know the
addition of milk
prevents the artery
protective effects of tea
and prevents the
bump in antioxidants
that you’d normally get
eating dark chocolate
and impairs
the absorption
of the autophagy-activating
compounds in coffee.
What about mixing
berries and cream?
The antioxidant activity of blueberries
is not just impaired by milk.
Researchers found that the total
antioxidant capacity of our bloodstream
(measured in two
different ways)
shoots up within an hour of eating
a cup-and-a-half (200 g) of blueberries with water
and remains elevated
five hours later.
With milk, maybe one
would expect less of a bump?
But in fact, they ended up even
worse than when they started.
After eating a whole
bowl of blueberries,
they ended up with less
antioxidant capacity in their body—
because they ate
blueberries with milk.
One reason greens may be referred
to as an anti-Alzheimer’s plant
is because dark green leafy vegetables
can also improve blood flow in the brain
in interventional trials.
Randomize older adults
to the greens pigments
found in about a cup (12 mg) a
day’s worth of cooked kale
and see significant improvements
in complex attention, cognitive flexibility.
And those randomized
to even just a half cup
of kale’s worth of the cruciferous
compound sulforaphane
got significant improvements in
processing speed and working memory.
Here’s the rate of cognitive
decline in elderly men and women
eating a serving a
day of green leafies,
compared to those only eating
greens about once every ten days.
Are you sitting down?
“The rates of decline
among those
who consumed 1 to 2
servings of greens a day
was the equivalent to
being 11 years younger… .”
So, now are you sitting
down to a big salad?
Greens come up in
chapter after chapter.
What’s the recommendation for preventing
age-related macular degeneration,
our leading cause
of blindness?
Or even treating it
in its earliest stages?
Consume a diet high
in green leafy vegetables.
We’re talkin’ two to
three servings a day,
so at least greens at
every lunch and supper,
with bonus points for sneaking them
into breakfast in, say, a green smoothie.
In fact, blending greens
can triple the bioavailability
of a key, vision-
protecting nutrient.
The main reason greens make
it into in my Anti-Aging 8 though,
is because of the nitrates in
a serving or two of cooked greens
can slow our metabolic
rate for the same reason,
a little shot of beet juice can help
free divers hold their breath longer,
because it improves the
efficiency of our mitochondria,
the little power
plants in our cells,
allowing us to effectively extract
more energy from each breath.
Another dietary intervention that has
a similar effect on slowing metabolism
is calorie restriction.
The candle that burns half
as bright burns twice as long.
But instead of starving all the time,
you can just eat a big salad.
What else can
greens do?
In the Harvard Nurses’
Health Study,
the consumption of leafy
greens appeared to protect
against the
development of frailty,
and when put to the test in a randomized,
double-blind, placebo-controlled trial,
the equivalent of two
thirds of a cup (158 ml) of spinach
led to a significant boost in
muscle strength, muscle quality,
and muscle mass in
older men and women.
A single cup (240 ml) of cooked greens
worth of vegetable nitrates
significantly boosted maximal power
and velocity in quads so much
it was “functionally equivalent,
to acutely reversing the effects
of several decades of aging.”
A single cup (240 ml)
of cooked greens!
Of course, when most people think
about maintaining muscle mass into old age,
they don’t think spinach,
they think protein.
But if you put together all of
the randomized, controlled trials
of adding extra protein to the
diets of older men and women,
you find no evidence that adding protein
increases muscle mass or strength.
Yeah, but what if you have sarcopenia,
excessive age-related muscle loss?
Surely then,
protein helps, right?
No.
No significant effect on physical
performance or muscle strength.
What does work?
Exercise.
When it comes to
age-related muscle loss,
it’s use it or lose it.
But maybe exercise
plus protein?
No.
Protein supplementation
does not significantly augment
the effects of strength
training in older adults.
In fact, one of my Anti-Aging 8
is protein restriction.
Why do longevity experts like Valter Longo
recommend people cut down on protein
to live longer?
Here’s what Luigi Fontana
wrote in his book.
He’s the director of another
leading longevity research center.
Excess protein may
not mass your muscles,
but it will accelerate aging.
How do you boost the
pro-longevity hormone FGF21?
Dietary protein restriction.
How do you suppress the
age-accelerating enzyme IGF-1?
You do it through dietary
protein restriction.
How do you suppress the
so-called motor of aging, mTOR?
Dietary protein restriction.
In fact, protein restriction was
the only intervention I could find
that could slow down all
11 of the aging pathways,
which is good news because
it’s easier to cut back on protein
than it is to cut
back on everything
and walk around
starving all the time.
And, it may even
be easier than that.
Most or all of the life-extending
benefits of protein restriction
may be due to just restricting
particular amino acids like methionine.
In that case, you could even
keep your protein intake the same
but just swap sources,
from animal proteins like meat
to plant-based sources like beans.
So, in humans,
methionine restriction can be achieved
using a predominately plant-based diet,
which makes methionine restriction
feasible as a life-extension strategy.
Of course, drug companies
look at this same data and think:
What pharmaceuticals can we develop
to mimic these dietary interventions?
Anything else to maintain muscle mass
other than greens and machines?
How about cocoa beans!
Older men and women randomized
to a single tablespoon (22 g)
of regular cocoa
powder a day
experienced a significant
improvement in muscle strength,
muscle mass, and all four
tests of physical performance.
And no, the study was
not funded by Hershey’s.
Unfortunately, the tastiest
cocoa doesn’t work as well.
The control groups here were given
the same amount of highly Dutched cocoa—
alkalized cocoa,
where some of the bitter compounds
removed in the Dutching process
are the very flavonoids
responsible for the benefits.
But natural cocoa is so good
it can improve walking performance
in those with peripheral artery disease,
not only by
improving blood flow,
but, as muscle
biopsies showed,
by improving
mitochondrial activity.
This is consistent with improved
mitochondrial structure
as well in biopsies taken
from people’s quads.
Though this study was
actually funded by Hershey’s.
What else can cocoa do?
Increase the circulation
within our skin,
boosting it 70 percent
within two hours,
after less than a tablespoon.
Do that every day and
within three months,
you end up with significantly
improved skin thickness,
density, and hydration,
but no change in wrinkles.
However, keep it
up for six months,
and you do see an
improvement in wrinkles,
a significant decrease
of wrinkle depth,
along with an improvement in
skin elasticity within 12 weeks—
all by making your life
a little more chocolatey,
by just adding some natural
cocoa powder to your daily diet.
I put it in my oatmeal with some
canned water-packed tart cherries
for a chocolate-covered
cherry sensation.
What else can we
do for our skin?
Well, there certainly
are other antioxidant,
anti-inflammatory,
glycotoxin-free foods;
so, when patients
inquire about a diet
that might contribute
to younger-looking skin,
evidence supports
a recommendation
to follow a whole food,
plant-based diet.
But the most important thing to
prevent skin aging is avoid the sun.
Exposure to sunlight may account
for 90 percent of visible skin aging.
That’s why
dermatologists agree
there’s nothing more important
to slow the signs of aging
than to protect your
skin from the sun.
So, the gold standard is considered
to be the use of sunscreens
in the daytime and
“retinoids” at night.
They’re talking about a prescription-
only form of topical vitamin-A,
also known as
all-trans-retinoic-acid,
or tretinoin
(sold as Retin-A),
that has been widely proven
to improve skin appearance.
The only problem is
that it may kill you.
“Topical Tretinoin Therapy
and All-Cause Mortality”,
a randomized controlled trial
had to be stopped early,
because significantly more people
were dying in the retinoic acid group,
compared to the
placebo-cream group.
When applied topically,
1 to 8 percent is absorbed
into the bloodstream.
Could it be
killing people?
While the debate
continues
as to whether the increase in deaths
was just some statistical fluke
or a real biological effect,
tretinoin continues to be banned
in Europe for cosmetic purposes.
So, what can we use?
Topical niacinamide,
also known as nicotinamide,
is described as one of the best-studied
anti-aging skin cream ingredients
(which is not
saying much),
but it has been shown
to reduce yellowing,
wrinkling, blotchiness,
and dark spots in aging facial skin,
for example, significantly reducing
crow’s feet wrinkles around the eyes.
This was a
split-face study
in which 64 percent of the
niacinamide-side eye wrinkles
had moderate or
marked improvement,
compared to zero percent
of the placebo-side eyes.
Topical vitamin C also offers similar
improvements over placebo in wrinkles,
sallowness, and
skin tone or firmness.
Unfortunately, vitamin C
is unstable in creams,
turning an unsightly
brown when it oxidizes,
limiting its shelf life.
So instead, what the
skin care industry does,
the skin care industry,
they use the stable
vitamin C esters or derivatives,
but there’s no evidence that these
compounds have comparable effects,
likely because they’re
poorly absorbed
and only minimally convert
to the active form.
But the good news is you
can make your own.
The 10 percent solution used in the study
retails for a ridiculous $127 an ounce (30 ml),
but you can make a DIY solution
more than two thousand times cheaper
by simply buying
ascorbic acid in bulk
and mixing three grams
into 30 grams of water,
at a cost of about
a nickel per ounce (30 ml).
Drip a few drops into
the palm of your hand
and use your fingertips to
apply it over your face,
neck, and upper chest daily.
(Just don’t get
it in your eyes.)
And look, you can do the
same thing with niacinamide,
which can be even
more ridiculously priced.
But you can buy
it in bulk as well,
at a 5,000 percent discount.
I can go on and on,
and the book certainly does,
but let me close out by
going back to the basics.
From the anti-aging journal
Rejuvenation Research:
“Finally, a regimen to extend
human life expectancy.”
Was it some exotic new stem
cell treatment or gene therapy?
No, it was a reference
to this Harvard analysis.
More than a hundred thousand men
and women were followed for decades,
and even just a few
basic lifestyle behaviors
appeared to translate into 12 to 14
extra years for the average 50-year-old.
Even at age 50,
you may be able to add an
extra dozen years to your lifespan.
Even at age 70,
there could still be about
ten extra years on the table.
And if you clean up
your life before 50,
nearly 18 years may
be up-for-grabs,
based on simple
common-sense behaviors.
That’s the kind
of life extension
extrapolating from some
of these lab animal experiments,
but after decades of research and
hundreds of millions of dollars later,
efforts to translate those results
into humans have largely been in vain.
Yet, here we are
with human data
suggesting dramatic life
extension is available to all of us.
Right here, right now.
The trillion-dollar pill that anti-aging
biotech has been promising us is here,
it just effectively has to be administered
in the produce aisle and the gym.
Turning back the clock,
not with a drug or a DeLorean,
but just by eating and
living more healthfully.
A midlife shift between
the ages of 45 and 64
to even the barest
of minimums,
the barest of minimums.
So, what are
we talking about?
At least 5 servings of
fruits and vegetables a day,
walking even just
20 minutes a day,
maintaining a
healthy weight,
and not smoking,
can result in a substantial
reduction in mortality
even in the immediate future.
We’re talking a 40
percent lower risk of dying
in the subsequent
four years.
The researchers conclude that
making the necessary changes
to adhere to a healthy lifestyle
is extremely worthwhile,
and middle-age is
certainly not too late to act.
You hold the power.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.